It is your duty to present your data in the most truthful way possible?
مهمتكم هي تقديم البيانات بأكثر الطرق الممكنة صدقًا.
People can and do lie with their visualizations to deceive others.
يمكن أن يكذب الأشخاص باستخدام المرئيات لخداع الآخرين.
One of the most common methods is in distorting the area of charts.
أحد أكثر الأساليب شيوعًا هو تشويه مساحة المخططات.
Here's an example from Fox News that was created in 2012.
إليكم مثال من قناة فوكس نيوز كان في عام 2012.
The chart here is attempting to show you the change in tax rate.
يحاول المخطط هنا إظهار لكم التغيير في معدل الضريبة.
It looks like a huge change.
يبدو تغييرًا كبيرًا.
Something like five times increase.
زيادة تقرب إلى خمسة أضعاف.
However, if you look at the actual numbers,
ورغم ذلك، إذا نظرتم إلى الأرقام الفعلية،
it's only 35 percent to 39.6 percent.
فإنها تتراوح ما بين 35 في المائة و39.6 في المائة فقط.
A 13 percent increase or 4.6 percentage points.
زيادة بنسبة 13 في المائة أو 4.6 نقاط مئوية.
Humans tend to assume that the baseline of a bar chart is set to zero.
يميل الأشخاص إلى افتراض أن خط الأساس في المخطط الشريطي يتم تعيينه على الصفر.
Here, the baseline was set to 34 percent,
تم تعيين خط الأساس هنا إلى 34 في المائة،
which is out of line with our assumptions.
وهو ما يتنافى مع افتراضاتنا.
The creator of this graphic,
تم إنشاء أداة إنشاء هذه الرسومات على الأرجح
likely meant to deceive viewers into believing
لخداع المشاهدين للاعتقاد
the tax rate change was much larger than it actually was.
بأن تغيير معدل الضرائب كان أكبر بكثير مما كان عليه في الواقع.
This brings us to the lie factor,
ويؤدي بنا ذلك إلى عامل الكذب،
a concept introduced by Edward Tufte in Visual Display.
وهو مفهوم قدمه إدوارد توفت في العرض المرئي.
Yup, him again.
نعم، هو مرة أخرى.
You really should find this book if you haven't yet.
يجب أن تحصلون على هذا الكتاب إذا لم تكونوا قد حصلتم عليه حتى الآن.
The lie factor compares the size of the effect in
يقارن عامل الكذب حجم التأثير في
a graphic to the size of the effect in the data.
الرسم بحجم التأثير في البيانات.
By effect, I mean the difference you're comparing.
في الواقع، أعني الفرق الذي تحصلون عليه في المقارنة.
For example, you're comparing the heights of the bars in the tax rate chart.
على سبيل المثال، أنتم تقارنون ارتفاعات الأشرطة في مخطط سعر الضريبة.
So the effect would be how much taller the right bar is than the left bar.
لذا فإن التأثير سيكون ما مدى كون الشريط الأيمن أطول من الشريط الأيسر.
To calculate the lie factor,
لحساب عامل الكذب،
you divide the effect size by the graphic with the effect size by the data.
تقومون بقسمة حجم التأثير في الرسم على حجم التأثير في البيانات.
As an example of this,
وكمثال على ذلك،
I'll use this figure,
سأستخدم هذا الشكل،
which is also a great example of chart junk.
الذي يكون أيضًا مثالًا رائعًا لرسم بياني غير هام.
It's actually ambiguous which aspect of the doctor images is encoded in the data.
من الغامض حقًا ترميز جانب صور الطبيب في البيانات.
The height, the area,
الارتفاع، المساحة،
it turns out the height of the doctors is proportional to the percentages.
اتضح أن ارتفاع الأطباء يتناسب مع النسب المئوية.
But we actually perceive the visual area as the encoding for the data.
لكننا في الواقع ندرك أن المساحة المرئية هي تشفير للبيانات.
Since we're comparing the area of the doctors,
وبما أننا نقارن مساحة الأطباء،
I'll use that to calculate the graphical effect.
سأستخدم ذلك لحساب التأثير الرسومي.
Making a rectangle around this largest doctor,
برسم مستطيل حول هذا الطبيب الأكبر،
it's 437 pixels tall and 181 pixels wide.
إن طوله يبلغ 437 بكسل وعرضه 181 بكسل.
So it has an area of around 79,000 square pixels.
لذلك تبلغ مساحته حوالي 79000 بكسل مربع.
The middle doctor has an area around 30,500 square
يشغل الطبيب المتوسط مساحة تبلغ حوالي 30500 بكسل مربع
pixels and the smallest doctor is 16,500 square pixels.
والطبيب الأصغر حوالي 16500 بكسل مربع.
Let's work out the lie factor for the comparison between 1964 and 1990.
دعونا نجعل عامل الكذب للمقارنة بين 1964 و1990.
The visual effect is how much larger the doctor is in 1964.
التأثير المرئي هو مدى كبر حجم الطبيب في 1964.
That is 79,000 minus 16,500 divided by 16,500 or 3.79.
يكون ذلك 79000 ناقص 16500 مقسومًا على 16500 أو 3.79.
So the difference between the size of the doctors is
لذا يكون الفرق بين حجم الأطباء هو
379 percent the size of the smaller doctor.
379 في المائة من حجم الطبيب الأصغر.
The effect size and the actual data is 27 minus 12 divided by 12, or 1.25.
حجم التأثير والبيانات الفعلية هو 27 ناقص 12 مقسومًا على 12 أو 1.25.
So the difference in the data is 125 percent larger than the 1990 data point.
وبالتالي، فإن الفرق في البيانات أكبر بنسبة 125 بالمائة من نقطة البيانات لعام 1990.
Dividing these, the lie factor is 3.0 or 3.
بقسمة ذلك، يكون عامل الكذب 3.0 أو 3.
Any lie factor greater than 1 suggests that your visual is misleading.
يقترح أي عامل كذب أكبر من 1 أن العنصر المرئي لديكم مضلل.
The larger the factor,
كلما كان العامل أكبر،
the more misleading the visual.
كان العنصر المرئي مضللًا أكثر.